Guide to the Kenny J. Williams Papers, 1971-1995
Duke University. University Archives
Kenny J. Williams papers 1971-1995
Duke University. University Archives
Williams, Kenny Jackson, 1927-2003.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 2, 000 Items
Kenny Williams was a professor of English at Duke University. Her collection includes memorabilia, correspondence, department memoranda and manuscripts.
RL.01950
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
For a period of twenty-five years from the origin of the material, permission in writing from the office of origin and the University Archivist is required for use. After twenty-five years, records that have been processed may be consulted with the permission of the University Archivist.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Kenny J. Williams Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 2004.
Biographical Note
Born in Omaha, NE, Kenny Williams grew up in Chicago where her father served as a Baptist pastor. She received a B.A. from Benedict College in 1949, her first M.A. degree from De Paul University in 1950, and her second M.A. and her Ph.D. from the University of Pennsylvania in 1959 and 1961, respectively. After teaching at Tennessee A and I State University, and at Northeastern Illinois State University, she joined the faculty of the Duke English Department in 1977, where she specialized in Midwestern and African-American literature. In 1991 she was nominated by President George H. W. Bush to the advisory counsel of the National Endowment for the Humanities. Among her published works include They Also Spoke: An Essay on Negro Literature in America, 1787-1930, In the City of Men: Another Story of Chicago, Prairie Voices: A Literary History of Chicago from the Frontier to 13 and A Storyteller for a City: Sherwood Anderson's Chicago. At the time of her death in 2003, Williams had been writing on literature of the Civil War era for the Dictionary of Literary Biography series.
Collection Overview
Contains greeting cards, brochures, correspondence, departmental memoranda, course materials, committee minutes, and manuscripts of Williams' article "The Masking of the Novelist" and her book In the City of Men: Another Story of Chicago. Also includes documents relating to the President's Council on Black Affairs, the Nixon Library controversy, and the Phi Beta Kappa selection committees. Minutes, private correspondence and reports of the English Department and the University should be restricted. Receipts, recommendation letters, grade disputes and ephemeral correspondence were discarded for processing. Correspondence was removed from envelopes and foldered.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
American literature 19th century Study and teaching (Higher).; American literature -- African American authors -- History and criticism theory, etc.; Duke University. Dept. of English -- Faculty.; National Endowment for the Humanities.; Williams, Kenny Jackson, 1927-2003.
Related Material
Department of English Records, 1926 – ongoing.
University Archives. Duke University.
Nixon Library Controversy Collection, 1981-2001.
University Archives. Duke University.
Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library Records, 1981.
University Archives. Duke University.
Black History at Duke Reference Collection, 1948-2001 and undated
University Archives. Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 2 Boxes
  - "The Masking of the Novelist" (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Cards, Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous Cards, Memorabilia
  - In the City of Men, manuscript
  - Correspondence, Department Memoranda, Memorabilia, 1986
  - Correspondence, 1975-1983 (RESTRICTED)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1985
  - Schmid Elementary School Condolences, 1979
  - Letter to Mrs. J. H. Jackson from Yuriko Kageura, 1962 Sept. 16
  - Photograph of Professors Kenny J. Williams and Dale B. J. Randall standing outside Williams' residence in Durham, NC
  - American Literature to 1865 (Box 2)
  - Afro-American Novel, 1853-1906
  - 1890s - Literary Profile
  - 169s.04 - Spring 1995
  - Department Documents, 1995
  - Department Documents, 1985-1986
  - Department Documents, 1985
  - Department Memoranda, Correspondence, 1981-1988
  - Friends of Art Museum Committee
  - Bevan (Provost) Memos
  - Minority Affairs and President's Council
  - Long-Range Planning Committee
  - Course Outlines - Miscellaneous
  - Presidential Council on Black Affairs
  - Advisory Committee on Afro-American Studies
  - Hiring Advisory Committee Memoranda
  - Curriculum Committee, 1986-1987
  - Afro-American Committee
  - President's Council
  - 267 - Outlines and Problems
  - Nixon Library
  - Nixon Flap
  - University Planning Committee Report, 1980
  - 177 - Rise of the American Novel
  - Letter to Chairman, 1977
  - Faculty Associates, Admissions
  - Department Documents, 1977-1978
  - Correspondence, 1977-1980
  - Department Documents, 1988-1991
  - Duke Retrenchment, Clippings, 1980
  - Admissions Decisions Committee
  - Academic Plan Draft, 1987
  - Directions for Progress - Report to the Board of Trustees, 1980
  - Phi Beta Kappa Committees and Bylaws
  - Spring Initiation Speaker, 1991